(upbeat music)
- Hello, English learners.
Welcome back to another
podcast here with us at English Pod.
My name is Marco.
- And I'm Erica.
- And today we have an
advanced lesson for all of you
and a very good one
because we're going to be
talking about a very
serious topic, global warming.
- That's right.
And, you know, even though most people
agree that global warming is a big problem,
there's still this sort of
fringe element of people who
believe that actually a
global warming doesn't exist.
- Exactly, so that's what we're
going to be looking at today,
but before we tell you more or
less what the dialogue is about,
let's take a look at some
words in vocabulary preview.
- Very capillary preview.
- We're going to look at two words here
and you'll hear both
of these in the dialogue.
So the first one is polar ice caps.
- Polar ice caps.
- So when we talk about polar
ice caps, polar is-- - Like the poles.
- The poles, right?
- The North and South poles of the Earth.
- Okay, so the extreme, the top and
bottom, the top and bottom of the planet.
- Yep.
- Okay, and what about ice caps?
- So the polar ice caps
are masses of ice that live
or that exist on the top
and the bottom of the world.
- We have these big chunks of ice that
are on the top at the bottom of the planet.
- Yes, they're there all year round.
- Okay, so these are the polar ice caps.
What about our next word?
- Well, next word is endangered species.
- And endangered species.
- Okay, so endangered species.
- It's a type of animal that is
at risk of completely dying out.
- Okay, so it's not completely extinct.
- Right.
- So they're still--
- It's a danger.
- Okay, in danger of, so an example of
endangered species would be the Bengal tigers.
- Okay, the tigers or the pandas, right?
- Or maybe gorillas.
- Right, so all of these
animals, there are very few of
them left in the world, so
they are endangered species.
- Okay, so with that, I think we're
just about ready to turn to our dialogue.
Now, here we're gonna
learn a lot of language
that you can use when you
want to make an argument or
express your point of view
in a very sort of academic way.
But Marco, what are we arguing about here?
- So we're gonna listen as a college
professor is lecturing about global warming,
and well, one of the students doesn't
really agree with what he's saying.
(upbeat music)
(crowd chattering)
- And therefore, global warming is the
greatest deception of the early 21st century.
Questions?
- Yeah, in the lecture you
said, there's more evidence
in the scientific record,
supporting global cooling.
- Well, yes.
Essentially, the historical
record supports a
theory of climate cycles,
warming and cooling
are cooperating processes
in the planetary ecosystem.
- If that's true, and the
planet is getting cooler,
what explains the rapid
melting of the polar ice caps
and the dramatic rise in the
global average temperatures?
- But our global temperature is rising.
If you look at the data from 1975, you'll--
- You'll be misled.
If you were serious, you
would look at the record
starting in the 1880s,
then you would see how
dramatically the Earth's
temperature has changed.
- Young lady, I beg to differ.
Look, the point of the lecture was to
emphasize that there's evidence for both sides,
and I'm putting forth the argument
that there's greater evidence
in support of the global
cooling hypothesis.
Look, it's an indisputable fact that the
public is being manipulated and scared
into believing that there's
some kind of climate crisis.
This scaremongering is done
quite simply for political reasons.
- But even without the
uncomfortable reality
that greenhouse gases like
carbon dioxide contribute
to global warming, isn't the topic
appropriate for politicians to discuss?
- Not if they want to
use your tax dollars and
mine to fund completely
unnecessary initiatives.
- Yeah, like conservation, protecting
endangered species and investing
in renewable energy, at the very least,
you have to concede that this debate
has the potential to end our
dependence on foreign oil.
Buying oil supports autocratic countries
that use these revenues to devastating ends.
- I've never been so
disrespected in all of my days.
I'm a professor, a scientist,
and a researcher of high regard.
- Yeah, and the duplicitous one at that.
- Everyone knows you're in
the pocket of the oil lobby.
Why should we trust your
so-called findings more than tobacco
institute studies, which say
smoking doesn't harm health.
You're full of it.
- Some people just
cannot handle civil debate.
- All right, so apparently
this college professor
is not very truthful in
what he's saying, right?
- Well, yeah, maybe he believes it,
but I certainly have very
strong and differing opinions.
- Mm-hmm, so that's the interesting part
is that we heard a lot of language
that she used to argue her point of view.
So this is interesting, and
we can start now looking
at some of this language
in language takeaway.
- Language takeaway.
- So the college professor was arguing
against this idea of global warming,
and she said, look,
it's an indisputable fact.
- Okay, an indisputable fact.
- An indisputable fact.
- Okay, so let's break it down, and let's
take a look at this word indisputable.
- You can't argue against it.
- Okay, so something
indisputable is you can't argue
with it, and will affect
something that's true.
- Okay, so you can't argue with this--
- This piece of information, yeah.
- All right, indisputable fact.
- So why don't we give a few examples?
It's an indisputable fact that China
is the most populous nation on earth.
- Okay, exactly.
Or it's an indisputable fact that
English part is the best podcast out there.
- Indeed, it is indisputable.
- All right, so indisputable fact.
And what about our next word?
- Well, the student accused
the professor of scaremongering.
- Scaremongering.
- Okay, now this is kind of a
strange word, scaremongering.
- Yeah, and I think some
examples will help us
to understand the
meaning a little bit better.
- Example one.
- Software flaws are not
the same as virus attacks,
and saying otherwise
is just scaremongering.
- Example two.
- There's been a lot of
scaremongering caused
by the rumor that mobile
phones cause cancer.
- Okay, so basically we understand that
it's kind of putting fear in people's minds.
- Yeah, it's sort of like selling
fear for your own benefit.
- Okay, so making people afraid
for some objective or some purpose.
- Yeah, and you know, this word
reminds me of the word a fishmonger.
- Okay, a fishmonger, what's that?
- Which is basically a seller of fish.
So a scaremonger is a seller of fear.
- Okay, interesting.
So now we have a way of remembering it.
- Yes.
- Scaremongering.
All right, and moving on to our
next word, we have autocratic.
- Autocratic.
- An autocratic country.
So an autocratic country is ruled
by someone who holds total power.
- Okay, so we have an autocratic country.
So basically we have a leader
that rules everything, right?
- Right.
- But we can apply it not only to a
country, we can say a person is autocratic.
- Yeah, you could say, "Oh, I can't stand
my boss's autocratic leadership style.
" - Or maybe a company.
This company is a very
autocratic organization.
- Okay, very good.
And what about our last word?
- The student accused the professor
of being duplicitous.
- Okay, so she said he is duplicitous.
- Yes, duplicitous.
- All right, what does that mean?
- When you are duplicitous,
you have behavior
that is dishonest and is
designed to trick people.
- Okay, so you're not a very
honest person if you're duplicitous.
- Yeah, you're telling lies as a means
of making people do
something or tricking them.
- Okay, very good.
So a duplicitous person or
a duplicitous idea maybe?
- Mm-hmm.
- Okay, all right, so
these are all the words
that we have on
language takeaway today,
but now let's move on to
some very interesting phrases
that we can use to put forward
some arguments in fluency builder.
- Fluency builder.
Okay, and Marker, you
actually just mentioned
our first phrase, which is, I'm
putting forth the argument that.
- Okay, so putting forth the argument that.
- Mm-hmm.
- So if you put forth an argument.
- You present it.
- You present it, or you
push it towards somewhere.
- Yeah, you give it.
- Uh-huh.
- So can we just put forth an argument?
- Well, actually you can put forth a
lot of things, like put forth a suggestion.
- Okay, I'm putting forth a suggestion
that we should get a new computer.
- Or an idea.
- Tim put forth the idea that we
should go on vacation to Hawaii.
- Mm-hmm, good idea.
- All right, so you can put
forth many different things.
- So the professor
obviously is putting forth
the argument that
global warming is a myth,
and the student obviously totally disagreed,
and she said you have to concede that.
- Okay, you have to concede that.
- You have to concede that.
- All right, so this word can
see it, or you have to concede.
Why don't we listen to some examples
before we listen to the meaning?
- Example one.
I'm sorry, but I can't concede
with you on this point.
- Example two.
- Julie conceded that she might
have forgotten her sister's birthday.
- Example three.
- Both philosophers conceded that
their philosophies have some errors.
- Okay, so you have to concede that.
Basically, you have to agree that
this one point in my argument is true.
- Maybe you're arguing many different
points with somebody, but you tell them,
"Well, you have to concede
that the earth is round.
" - Okay, so that
part, I can't argue with.
It's really true.
- Okay, very good.
So concede.
Now, at the end of the dialogue,
the student accused the professor
of being in the pocket of the oil lobby.
- Okay, so he's in the pocket
of, to be in the pocket of.
- All right, so if I have somebody
in my pocket, what does that mean?
- It means basically you're bribing them.
- Okay, so maybe I have
the senator in my pocket.
- Okay, so obviously you're paying
the senator to do what you want.
- Okay, very good.
So it's another way, it's a
very informal way of saying,
I'm bribing somebody, or
that person is being bribed.
- That's right.
- So why don't we move to our final phrase?
And the students was talking about
the professors so-called findings.
- Okay, so you're so-called findings.
- So-called.
- So this word so-called.
- You use this word when you wanna
take away from the importance of an idea.
- Or, all right, so I use
it before a noun, right?
- Right, so for example,
my so-called friends.
- Okay, so these friends are
not really your friends, maybe.
- So yeah, they're friends in
name, but they don't act like friends.
- Okay, so you can say my so-called job.
- Okay, so maybe you kind of
go to work, but do nothing all day.
- Right, or maybe you don't
even really like what you do.
- Right.
- Right, so my so-called job, my so-called
friends, or maybe my so-called teacher.
- Okay, so this is a bad teacher.
- Exactly, so we use it a lot
with many different nouns, right?
- That's right, so that's our
last phrase for Fluency Builder.
Now, I think it'll help us to
understand these words and
phrases a little bit better to
hear them again in context.
(upbeat music)
- And therefore, global warming is the
greatest deception of the early 21st century.
Questions?
- Yeah, in the lecture you
said, there's more evidence
in the scientific record,
supporting global cooling.
- Well, yes.
Essentially, the historical record
supports a theory of climate cycles.
Warming and cooling are cooperating
processes in the planetary ecosystem.
- If that's true, and the
planet is getting cooler,
what explains the rapid
melting of the polar ice caps
and the dramatic rise in the
global average temperatures?
- But our global temperature is rising.
If you look at the data from 1975, you'll--
- You'll be misled.
If you were serious, you would look
at the record starting in the 1880s.
Then you would see how dramatically
the Earth's temperature has changed.
- Young lady, I beg to differ.
Look, the point of the lecture was to
emphasize that there's evidence for both sides.
And I'm putting forth the argument
that there's greater evidence
in support of the global
cooling hypothesis.
Look, it's an indisputable fact that the
public is being manipulated and scared
into believing that there's
some kind of climate crisis.
This scaremongering is done
quite simply for political reasons.
- But even without the
uncomfortable reality
that greenhouse gases like
carbon dioxide contribute
to global warming, isn't the topic
appropriate for politicians to discuss?
- Not if they want to
use your tax dollars and
mine to fund completely
unnecessary initiatives.
- Yeah, like conservation,
protecting endangered
species and investing
in renewable energy.
At the very least, you have
to concede that this debate
has the potential to end our
dependence on foreign oil.
Buying oil supports autocratic countries
that use these revenues to devastating ends.
- I've never been so
disrespected in all of my days.
I'm a professor, a scientist,
and a researcher of high regard.
- Yeah, and the duplicitous one at that.
Everyone knows you're in
the pocket of the oil lobby.
Why should we trust your
so-called findings more than tobacco
institute studies, which says
smoking doesn't harm health.
You're full of it.
- Some people just
cannot handle civil debate.
(upbeat music)
- All right, very good.
So interesting ways of putting
forth arguments, and well,
it's an interesting topic
and very controversial, right?
- That's right, but what
I noticed in this dialogue
is that the student was pretty
assertive in putting forth her argument
and standing up to the teacher.
- Right, she argued with
a teacher a lot, and this is
interesting because it's a very
cultural aspect, I think, right?
- Yeah, in North American universities,
there is this idea that it's really important
to think critically and to
argue against different ideas
and to really speak up when
you don't agree with something.
- Right, so basically there's
this culture of questioning,
not only what you're being taught,
but you can also question the teacher.
You don't actually have to believe
everything that the teacher is saying.
- Exactly, and actually, I think
this situation is really interesting.
You always go to these lectures, and
there's always a question and answer period
at the end of the lectures, and
I think that there's this group
of academically-minded
people who feel like it's really cool
to ask these really difficult questions
and engage in arguments with the props.
- Yeah, yeah, that's really true.
But actually, she used
a lot of polite language
in a lot of polite ways of
actually arguing with the professor
until the last point when
she said you're full of it.
- Yeah, you're full of it.
- Right, you're full of it.
- So what she's saying here?
- All right, she's basically
saying that you're full of shit.
- Where'd it go?
- So yeah, you wouldn't really say that.
So to be a little bit less rude,
you would just say you're full of it.
- Yeah, but that is one step too far.
I think this would be
considered a little bit rude.
- Yeah, for a professor, yeah.
But I guess if you don't believe
what your friend is telling you
or maybe he's exaggerating,
you can say, oh, you're full of it.
- Yeah, okay.
So some great argument of
language here in this dialogue,
but we wanna give you an opportunity
to try out some of this language.
So come to our website at EnglishPod.com.
- Right, we are there to answer any questions
or doubts and we'll see you guys there.
- All right, guys, until
next time, goodbye.
- Bye.
(upbeat music)